Records of the Coalition on West Valley Nuclear Wastes
State University of New York at Fredonia
The Records of Coalition on West Valley Nuclear Wastes
1964-2015
The Records of the Coalition on West Valley Nuclear Wastes documents activities of the Coalition while monitoring the operations of the West Valley Nuclear Waste site in Western New York, including government and corporate documents that the Coalition collected.
3 carton, 41 legal, 6 flat, and 4 roll storage boxes Approximately 31.5 linear feet
Coalition on West Valley Nuclear Wastes
State University of New York at Fredonia Archives & Special Collections Daniel A. Reed Library 280 Central Avenue Fredonia, NY 14063
This collection was made possible by a grant from the Documentary Heritage Program of New York State Archives in 2018/2019.
Further accruals are expected every five years.
MSS 43 Records of the Coalition on West Valley Nuclear Wastes, 1956-2008
Arranged in four series: I: Coalition on West Valley Nuclear Wastes’ Files, 1987-2015. II. Raymond C. Vaughan’s Files, 1964-2010. III. Legal Files, 1980-2012, and IV. Memorabilia, 1961-2008.
This set of records was donated as a second acquisition of Records of the Coalition on West Valley Nuclear Wastes in September 2015.
The records of Coalition on West Valley Nuclear Wastes are mainly open for research. Consult Archivist for some closed and restricted items.
Use of materials from this collection is governed by the Copyright Law of the United States (Title 17, U.S.C.). The Archives & Special Collections typically does not hold the copyright for materials in its collections. It is the sole responsibility of the researcher to determine any copyright status of the material intended for use outside that established by the U.S. Copyright Fair use doctrine and to gain the necessary permissions.
Please refer to biographical/historical notes on MSS 43 Records of the Coalition on West Valley Nuclear Wastes, 1956-2008 for Joanne Hameister (b. 1941), Carol Mongerson (1927-2005), and Raymond C. Vaughan (b. 1944).
Judy Einach (b.1948) The first-ever paid staff member in the 32-year history of the Coalition on West Valley Nuclear Wastes in 2006. She is well known as an independent candidate for Mayor of the City of Buffalo in 2005 and New York State Assembly (150th District) in 2018. Her past and present experience includes Director of Program Development for the Boys & Girls Club of Buffalo, Community Builder with United Neighborhood, Associate Director of Voice of the Arab World, Board Member of Citizen Action, and a leader of New York Sustainable Agriculture Working Group.
Robert E. Knoerr: He has been practicing law in Western New York for more than 30 years with extensive experience in environmental site review, remediation, consulting, and litigation (not only for the West Valley Nuclear Wastes site but also the Brownfield Cleanup Program), as well as renewable energy development and siting. His past and present involvement with a number of professional organizations includes Chairman of Air and Waste Management Association at Niagara Frontier Section, President of Erie County Environmental Education Institute, Board of Directors of the Engineering Society of Buffalo, and Advisory Board and Chair of Steering Committee of Western New York Environmental Alliance
affidavits; Western New York Nuclear Service Center; agendas (administrative records); annual reports; banners; case files; clippings files; correspondence; decisions (judicial records); federal government records; manuscripts for publication; minutes (administrative records); newspapers; transcripts; Sierra Club; Einach, Judy.; Hameister, Joanne.; Mongerson, Carol.; Knoerr, Robert.; Vaughan, Raymond C.; United States. Atomic Energy Commission (now Nuclear Regulatory Commission); United States. Congress. House; United States. Department of Energy. Office of Environmental Management; United States. Food and Drug Administration; United States. Environmental Protection Agency; United States. Federal District Court; United States. Federal Energy Research and Development; United States. General Accounting Office; U.S. Nuclear Regulatory Commission; New York (State). Advisory Committee on Low Level Radioactive Waste; New York State Energy Research and Development Authority; New York (State). Department of State; New York (State). Congress. Senate; New York (State). Department of Environmental Conservation; New York (State). Department of Health; New York (State). Low Level Radioactive Waste Siting Committee; New York (State). Office of the Attorney General; Radioactive waste sites --New York (State).; Radioactive waste sites--Cleanup--New York (State)--West Valley.; Radioactive waste disposal--Law and Legislation--New York (State).
The Records of the Coalition on West Valley Nuclear Wastes documents Coalition activities while monitoring and suing the operations of the West Valley Nuclear Wastes site in Western New York and responsible government agencies. It comprises government and corporate documents collected by the Coalition and publications by the Coalition. The depositories came from Coalition members Judy Einach (1948-present; Coalition president, 2006-present), Carol Mongerson (1927-2005), and Raymond C. Vaughan, and Coalition attorney Robert Knoerr. The contributor is sometimes noted on the corner of each page as follows: Einach [JH], Mongerson [CM], and Vaughan [RV]. For most of the collection, the archivist kept provenance and original order of each contributor’s records by creating specific series/subseries. However, archivist notes ([ ]) indicate separated items due to the size of boxes. Also, please be aware of archivist notes ([closed, or restricted]) for further details, since some documents are restricted. A section entitled “includes” after the folder level description does not attempt to describe everything in the folder, but rather highlights some significant items to give a sense of the folder’s contents.
Series I. Coalition on West Valley Nuclear Wastes’s Files contain mainly Judy Einach’s documents. Subseries A. Meeting/Conferences contain meeting- and conference-related correspondence, notes, schedules, and supplements since the Coalition participated in a significant number of meetings. Those meetings have been sponsored by state and federal government agencies: Citizen Advisory Meeting (a.k.a. pig, public, or technical meeting); NRC’s Advisory Committee on Nuclear Wastes meeting; New York Low-Level Waste Management Siting Committee meeting (a.k.a. Siting meeting); NYSERDA’s board and roundtable meetings; and West Valley Program Committee meeting of the New York State Attorney General’s Office (which was formed to assist citizens’ and groups’ interactions and discussions during federal and state-sponsored meetings). Sometimes, state and federal sponsored meetings were combined to meet their purposes. The Coalition’s own meetings are steering committee and pig or technical meeting. A long-standing Coalition member, Raymond C. Vaughan’s Files in Series II, contain those meeting/conference files, as well.
Series II of Raymond C. Vaughan’s Files contain documents produced by, researched by, commented on, or specifically requested by the Coalition, including records of activities of the Coalition while monitoring and studying the operations of the West Valley Nuclear Wastes site, communication among the members, and correspondence with government officials. Health, environmental, and technical matters on the site are significant in this series.
Subseries C. D. E of Series III. Legal Files contain court documents including Affidavits and Records of Decision. Subseries A. contains information from legislatures and government agencies, government-sponsored meetings, and collected information from professionals in different health or technical fields that relate to nuclear wastes and the site management. The Coalition’s civil action lawsuit case was about violating both cleanup standards of National Environmental Policy Act and a 1987 settlement between the Coalition and DOE by issuing an environmental statement concerning waste management activities at the West Project site, but didn’t address long-term closure issues of the rest of the Western New York Nuclear Service Center. Coalition attorney Robert Knoerr’s research and files are mainly gathered in the series.
Subseries A. Carol Mongerson Manuscript of Series III contains significant footage of the West Valley site, interviews with workers during Nuclear Fuel Services operation time as well as residents’ interviews, and her views as a government watchdog activist. Footnotes and clippings extend the author’s field research on working conditions at facilities from earlier to the late 1980s, and development of site regulations and policies over the decades from a citizen’s point of view. Her unpublished manuscripts, Silent Rape, Waste Valley, and West Valley, are also included in the subseries. Also within the Series are members’ collections of banners, newspaper clippings, paintings, photos, and posters.
- I:Coalition on West Valley Nuclear Wastes’ Files, 1987-2015
- A. Meetings/Conferences, 1998-2015
- Citizen Task Force Meetings [gaps, 65 folders], 1998-2014
- PIG Meetings [incomplete], 2007
- Quarterly Public Meetings [gaps, 9 folders], 2006-2015
- B. Director’s Subject Files, 1987-2013
- Burns, George, 2008
- Coalition’s Affiliates, 2007
- Coalition’s Comments, 2008
- Coalition’s Events, 2006
- Coalition for Economic Justice, 2006
- Dig up, 2006
- Coalition’s letter from director, 2006
- Coalition’s leadership, 2009
- Coalition’s past publications, 1990
- Coalition’s Prints, 2004-2007
- Coalition/Steering Committee, 2006-2008
- Correspondence, 2004-2006
- Department of Energy, 2006-2011
- Directory/Town of Concord and Springville, 2005
- Environmental Justice Impact Grant, 2008
- Environmental Protection Agency, 2007
- Hahn Family Foundation, 2008
- Legal Authorities and Obligations of Department of Energy, NYSERDA, and NRC, 2002-2008
- Love Canal, 2008
- New York State Department of Environmental Conservation, 2006-2007
- New York State Department of State, 2007
- New York State Energy Research and Development Authority [7 folders], 2005-2011
- New York State Senate, 2006
- Norman Foundation, 2008
- Nuclear Information and Resource Service, 2006-2008
- Nuclear Power: The Energy Balance, 2006
- Random Thinking on West Valley, 2007
- The State University of New York at Fredonia [2 folders], 2008-2013
- State of New York Office of the Attorney General, 2008
- Stipulation of Compromise Settlement, 1987
- Synapse, 2008
- Technocracy Inc., 2008
- Titian, 2009
- Toxic in Tonawanda [3 folders], 2007
- Unyse Lab, 2008
- URS, 2008
- Western New York Environmental Alliance, 2009
- West Valley Action Network, 2007
- West Valley Citizen Task Force [2 folders], 2006-2008
- West Valley Demonstration Project [oversize], 2010
- West Valley Environmental Service LLC, 2006-2008
- West Valley Nuclear Compensation Support Group, 2007-2008
- West Valley Nuclear Site, 2003-2006
- West Valley Regulatory Structure, 2006
- West Valley Workers’ Health, 2008
- Young, Catharine A., 2007
- C. Media/Publications, 1990-2013
- 2002-2009
- Buffalo News [oversize], 2007-2013
- Clippings, 2006-2007
- Local Media List, 2008
- WBFO Comments
- My Name is Allegany County [DVD], 1990
- Statement on FCA Study Release, 2008
- UTNE Reader, January/February issue, 2008
- II: Raymond C. Vaughan’s Files, 1964-2010
- A. Subject Files, 1964-2010
- Affidavit of Raymond C. Vaughan, 1986
- Anecdotal, 1980-1981
- Anecdotal, 2015
- Argonne National Laboratory, 1980
- Battelle, 1978-1981
- Bross, Irwin D.J. Ph.D., 1980
- Cattaraugus Community Action, Inc., 1981
- Clippings, 1964-1995
- Coalition on West Valley Nuclear Wastes, 1974-2003, 1974-2009
- Committee on Science and Technology U.S. House of Representatives, 1979-1986
- Department of Energy, 1978-2003
- Duffy, Gloria C., 1978
- Fernald Citizens Task Force, 1994-1995
- General Accounting Office, 1980
- Great Lakes Water Quality Board, 1977
- Gridley Lee, 2010
- Hancock, Trevor, Dr., 1991
- Health and Radiation, 1988-1994
- Interagency Review Group on Nuclear Waste Management, 1978
- League of Women Voters Education, 1979-1980
- Lobbying, 1984
- National Cancer Institutional Study, 1990
- Newsletter, 1981-1993
- New York State Department of Health, 1989-1990
- New York State Energy Office, 1981
- Nuclear Fuel Services, Inc, undated
- Nuclear Regulatory Commission, 1977-1991
- Nuclear Waste Management, 1979-1983
- Nuclear Waste Symposium, 1978
- Office of Environmental Management, 1997
- Olson, McKinley C., 1976
- Origin and Overview of the West Valley Nuclear Waste Site, 2003
- Pacific Northwest Laboratory, 1978-1981
- Periodical/Report Request, 1981
- Physicians for Social Responsibility, 1992
- Properties of Calcines, 1979
- Public Citizen, 1989
- Retrievability Project, 1987
- Sierra Club/Radioactive Waste Campaign, 1985
- Solar Energy Research Institute, 1980
- State-Licensed Burial Ground, 1979
- State of New York, 1980
- Technology Review, 1977
- United Way, 1981
- University at Buffalo, 1984
- Washington Hearing, 1979
- Western Valley Nuclear Service Company, 1999-2005
- West Valley Program Committee, 1981
- White House Press Briefing, 1980
- World Information Service on Energy, 1978
- Others, circa 1990
- III: Legal Files, 1978-2012
- A. Legal Research Files (preparatory material also included), 1992-2012
- B. Client Files, 1980-2012
- B. Client Files, 1980-2012
- C. Coalition v. Department of Energy, 86-1052-C, 1986
- D. Coalition v. Department of Energy, 05-CV-064, 2005
- E. Coalition v. Department of Energy, 07-5243-CV, 2007
- F. Others, 1996-2010
- IV.Memorabilia, 1961-2008
- A. Carol Mongerson Manuscript Papers, 1961-2002
- AEC Inspection, 1968-1974
- Chaffee Hospital, 1972-1974
- Chronology, 1961-1977
- Citizen of Year, 1992
- Clippings, 1976
- Clippings, “Track Explosion”, 1990
- Correspondence, 1979-1998
- Environmental Monitoring Report, 1985-1986
- Floppy Disks [8 disks], 1997-1998
- Interview with Carol and Joyce Bly, 1990
- Publisher’s file, 1996
- Lynch, David E., undated
- Western New York Nuclear Service Center: West Valley, 1961-1978
- Silent Rape, 1980-1998
- Silent Rape, circa 1980
- Silent Rape, 1990
- Silent Rape, 1991
- Silent Rape, 1996
- Silent Rape, 1998
- Silent Rape, undated [restricted], circa 1990
- Silent Rape/Footnotes; includes footnotes of Chapter 1-6 and 8-10, undated
- Silent Rape/Footnotes; includes Chapter 3 of Skinner file [closed], undated
- Silent Rape/Others; includes Chapter of Filter Blowout, undated
- Waste Valley, 1979-1989
- Waste Valley/Draft, 1979
- 1980
- Waste Valley/Chapter 8, 1989
- West Valley, 2002
- West Valley: Nuclear Waste, a Citizen’s view, 2002
- Subseries B. Banner, Photo, Poster and etc, 1970-2007
- Alternative II Posters, undated
- “Dig it up!” Banner, 2003
- “Dig it up!” Sticker, 2003
- Indian Summer Fest Poster, undated
- “No Nuclear Wastes at West Valley” Sticker, undated
- Postcards of meeting announcements, 2001-2007
- Posters of West Valley Site Maps, undated
- Public Hearing Poster, undated
- Radio Half Life Banner, undated
- Stickers, 2003
- “Stop the Dump” Button, undated
- Photograph, circa 1970
- Watercolor Painting, 2003
- C. Newspapers, 1990-2008
- Buffalo News, 1990-2013
- Clippings, 1990-2008
- Springville Journal, 1991-1999
- Other Clippings, 1990-1999